Register to Ethel Smyth: Letters and Scrapbook
Yale University Music Library
Ethel Smyth: Letters and Scrapbook
1877-1944
Misc. Ms. 418
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Letters from the British composer Ethel Smyth (1858-1944) and a scrapbook of clippings and programs concerning Smyth's compositions
Smyth, Ethel, 1858-1944
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment. Some of the materials may be stored at the Library's off-campus shelving facility, so researchers should allow at least two business days to have the appropriate boxes paged.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of this collection was purchased as Sotheby's in 1998. It has been augmented by later purchases.
Arrangement
In 3 series as follows: Series I. Correspondence. Series II. Other Items. Series III. Later Additions.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains letters from Ethel Smyth, chiefly to her sister Alice Davidson. Their dates range from 1877 to 1939, but the largest number are from 1916 to 1919. The letters discuss Smyth's education in Germany, her career as a composer, her work as an activist for women's suffrage, and other matters. The collection also includes a scrapbook of clippings and programs concerning Smyth's compositions from 1890 to 1893, as well as a handwritten biographical notice.
Biographical / Historical
Ethel Smyth was born in London on April 22, 1858. After receiving her early musical training in England, she entered the Leipzig Conservatory in 1877. She left the Conservatory in 1878, but continued her studies with Heinrich von Herzogenberg. During her years in Germany, she came to know many important musicians, including Brahms, Clara Schumann, and Grieg.
Smyth came to prominence in England in the early 1890s, with performances of her Serenade and Antony and Cleopatra in 1890 and the Mass in D in 1893. (These performances are the focus of the scrapbook in this collection.) She then turned her efforts to the stage. Over the next thirty years, she composed six operas: Fantasio, Der Wald, The Wreckers, The Boatswain's Mate, Fête galante, and Entente cordiale.
Beginning in 1910, Smyth was an important figure in the drive to gain women the right to vote in England, a movement led by her friend Emmeline Pankhurst. Smyth composed a suffragist anthem, and went to prison for throwing a rock through a window of the Colonial Secretary's home.
In the final three decades of her life, Smyth increasingly suffered from hearing loss. She continued to compose, but she devoted much of her time to a series of autobiographical books that vividly display her colorful and energetic personality. By the time of her death in Woking, England on May 8, 1944, she had long been recognized as the leading British female composer of her era.
Smyth, Ethel, 1858-1944 -- Correspondence; Women composers -- Correspondence -- England; Davidson, Alice -- Correspondence
- Correspondence, Series I
  General
  Smyth's handwriting is often difficult to read, so in some cases the names and dates listed below must be regarded as provisional. In other instances, names or dates were inferred from the contents of the letter; these, too, should not necessarily be taken as authoritative. Certain items bear dates that appear to have been added later by someone other than Smyth; these are noted as "date in pencil."
  - Boosey, Mr., Mar. 8, 1939
    Date hard to read.
  - [Camera?], Norman, 1935
    Postcard. Year in pencil; postmark date and surname hard to read.
  - Coates, John, Sr, Jan. 1, 1935
    Postcard.
  - Davidson, Alice, 1877
    Year inferred from content. From Leipzig.
  - Davidson, Alice, 1878
    Year in pencil. From Leipzig.
  - Davidson, Alice, 1889
    Year inferred from content.
  - Davidson, Alice, Dec. 22, 1889
    Year inferred from content. From Munich.
  - Davidson, Alice, July 6, 1900
  - Davidson, Alice, 1911
  - Davidson, Alice, Sept. 14, 1916
    Envelope also includes letter dated Sept. 22.
  - Davidson, Alice, Oct. 9, 1916
    Year in pencil; 2nd page of letter dated Oct 14.
  - Davidson, Alice, Nov. 30, 1916
    From Paris; year in pencil.
  - Davidson, Alice, Jan. 13, 1917
    From Paris.
  - Davidson, Alice, May 3, 1917
    From Vichy.
  - Davidson, Alice, June 7, 1917
  - Davidson, Alice, July 31, 1917
    Year in pencil on letter and envelope.
  - Davidson, Alice, Jan. 21, 1918
    Envelope only, contains no letter; postmarked Friedland.
  - Davidson, Alice, Mar. 31, 1918
    In same envelope as April 9 letter.
  - Davidson, Alice, Apr. 9, 1918
    From "Paris during bombardment."
  - Davidson, Alice, Apr. 24, 1918
  - Davidson, Alice, May 7, 1918
  - Davidson, Alice, May 14, 1918
  - Davidson, Alice, June 22, 1918
  - Davidson, Alice, Nov. 26, 1918
  - Davidson, Alice, Dec. 17, 1918
  - Davidson, Alice, Feb. 6, 1919
  - Davidson, Alice, Feb. 14, 1919
  - Davidson, Alice, Mar. 27, 1919
    Pages 1-2 ripped in half.
  - Davidson, Alice, May 6, 1919
  - Davidson, Alice, June 20, 1919
    From Seine-et-Oise, France.
  - Davidson, Alice, July 1, 1919
    From La Bourboule, France. Year hard to read.
  - Davidson, Alice, Jan. 19, 1938
  - Davidson, Alice, Jan. 23, 1938
    Postmarked 22 Jan 1938.
  - Davidson, Alice, Jan. 30, 1938
    Salutation reads "Darling Ethel," but it is from Ethel Smyth.
  - Davidson, Alice, Feb. 1, 1938
  - Godley, General, July 12, 1921
  - Hadley, Mrs. G., Jan. 23, 1924
  - Hadley, Mrs. G., Feb. 14, 1924
  - Harry, No date
    No salutation or envelope, but recipient is twice addressed as "Dear Harry" in course of letter. From Grove House.
  - Hattan, Mr., Nov. 7, 1928
  - Lears, Mr., Oct. 24, 1929
    Name hard to read.
  - Lyle, Watson, Feb. 24, 1937
  - Perceval-Hart, Mrs. E., July 29, 1939
    Envelope only, no letter.
  - Marchesi, Madame
    See: Series III, Later Additions
  - Newman, Ernest
  - [Smyth?], Bob, Mar. 24
    Date in pencil on second page. Year not given. From Paris during wartime.
  - [Smyth?], Bob, Feb. 14, 1918
    From Bob to Alice. Date hard to read.
  - Steen, Marguerite, Jan. 11, 1934
  - Whelen, Mr., Mar. 5
    Year not given.
  - No name, Sept. 22, 1930
    Begins "My dear Madam."
  - No name, Oct. 15, 1930
    Begins "Dear Sir."
  - No name, Oct. 21, 1930
- Other Items, Series II
  - Criticisms of E.M. Smyth's compositions from Oct. 1890, 1890-1893; [c. 100 p.]; 24 cm.
    Scrapbook consisting chiefly of clippings of reviews of works by Ethel Smyth. Also includes some concert programs.
    Works discussed: Serenade, Antony and Cleopatra, and the Mass in D major.
  - Biographical notice, 1 card (both sides); 15 x 10 cm.
    Scope and Contents
    Biographical notice; author unidentified.
    Undated, but was written after Smyth's death in 1944.
    In very small handwriting, in blue and red ink.
    Newspaper photograph, dated 1934, pasted on.
- Later Additions, Series III
  The items in this Series were acquired after the initial purchase of Smyth materials in 1998, and they were not included in the initial microfilm.
  - Marchesi, Madame, Aug. 4, 1941
  - Newman, Ernest, May 16, 1915
  - Newman, Ernest, May 17, 1915; Postcard.
  - Newman, Ernest, Nov. 24, 1919
  - Newman, Ernest, Jan. 13, 1922
  - Newman, Ernest?, Feb. 22, 1927
    The name on the envelope is Henry Newman, but the letter concerns music and is addressed to the Sunday Times, (where Ernest Newman was the music critic). Since this letter came to Yale with others from Ernest Newman, it seems likely that "Henry" was merely a mistake.
  - Newman, Ernest, July 3, 1927